上溯至宇宙初始 周遭还只是一片漆黑
In the beginning, there was darkness.
不知何时 忽地一声巨响
And then... Bang!
时间空间以及物质皆由此发端
Giving birth to an endless expanding existence
此后不断膨胀 延伸 永无止境
of time, space, and matter.
每一天 新的发现都在不断为我们解开
Every day, new discoveries are unlocking
蕴藏于这里的那些神秘莫测
the mysterious, the mind-blowing,
令人大开眼界 致命的秘密
the deadly secrets of a place we call
我们称这个地方为"宇宙"
the universe.
你在一个陌生的星球举步维艰
You're lost on an alien planet.
食物所剩无几
Food is running low.
氧气补给日渐减少
Oxygen is running out.
救助也在遥不可及的地点
Help is 100 million miles away.
火星是一个致命的地方
Mars, it's a lethal place.
哪里才能避免受宇宙辐射的伤害
Where can you hide from blasts of space radiation?
带电粒子会射向我们地表的宇航员
Charged particles would be hitting any astronauts that we had on the surface.
他们没有防护措施
They would not be protected.
如何才能抵御致命的尘暴
How can you stand up to a deadly dust storm?
火星上的尘土能侵蚀掉航天服
The dust on Mars could eat away at the fabric of a space suit.
这是非常可怕的
That would be catastrophic.
氧气不足时 你该怎么办
What will you do when you run out of air?
你会非常痛苦地死去
You will die a horrible death.
紧急降落火星后 你如何能够生还
How can you survive crash-landing on Mars?
宇宙:迫降火星
人类迫降在火星上
Humans crash landing on Mars.
在恶劣的环境中求生存
Struggling to survive on a hostile world.
这一直是科幻电影热门的素材
It's been a favorite theme of science-fiction movies.
这其中有许多事都搞错了
They got a lot of things wrong.
可是包括美国在内的许多国家的宇航局
But NASA and other space agencies
正筹备要在未来几十年内将人类送上火星
are planning to send people to the red planet in the next few decades.
所以我们要考虑火星上迫降和生存的问题
So the questions of crash-landing and survival have to be taken seriously.
要知道 你要做的事情
Well, think about what you're trying to do.
是将探索队送上火星
You're sending a mission to Mars,
着陆地点和环境都是你一无所知的
you're sending it to an unknown location within an unknown environment.
一步走错
All it takes is one thing to go wrong...
整盘皆输
Then you've lost the whole mission.
本节目是根据最近的科研成果
This program, based on recent scientific information,
展示了不久的将来可能发生的情景
presents one possible scenario of what might happen in the near future.
火星探索队 第174天 即将登陆
想象一下 国际探索队将去探索火星
Imagine that international crew has been selected to explore Mars
并为建立永久基地做好准备
and set the stage for a permanent base.
老电影中的这些人智勇双全 技能熟练
In old movies, such crews were brave, skilled, and resourceful.
电影的这一部分倒是说对了
Well, the movies got that part right.
总之 我们选拔人才组成一个小的团队
The bottom line is that when we're dealing with a small group of individuals
而不是一大群人时
forming a crew, not a large community,
有一个起码的标准
but a small group of people,
每一个人员的选拔都非常重要
the specific individuals that you end up selecting is really very important.
你会把谁送上火星呢
Who would you send to Mars?
不是那些杂而不精的人
Not jacks of all trades, uh, who are aces at none.
你希望你的团队每个方面都有能手
You want, uh, aces at many trades on your crew.
队员最重要的能力就是维修能力
The most important skill among the crew is that of mechanic.
四人团队中我要有两人
I would have two of the four members of the crew
是能够维修机械的
selected primarily for their ability to fix things.
除了机械师 团队中最重要的技能人才
After mechanic, the most important skill among the crew
是实地考察科学家 他们能够
is that of field scientist, people that are qualified to
根据地质线索找到化石
follow hints in the geology to find fossils
或是找到可开采的水源
or to find places where we can drill for water,
用《星际迷航》的话说
okay, in Star Trek terminology,
一个是机械师 一个是科学家
要两个史考特和两个斯波克
two Scottys and two Spocks.
还有一点是老电影里弄错了的
But here's something old movies got wrong,
即人类只需一艘尖头宇宙飞船便可抵达火星
the idea that humans will fly to Mars in a single needle-nosed spaceship.
与那些旧时的科幻电影中看到的不同
Unlike the case in many old science-fiction movies,
用多艘宇宙飞船将物资送去火星
it's actually cheaper and more efficient
会更低廉也更高效
to send a bunch of material to Mars on different rocket ships.
你要是想只用一艘飞船装载所有物资
If you try to put them on one rocket ship,
那就需要一艘巨型飞船
it turns out that that ship has to be enormous
甚至需要核能推动
and probably nuclear-powered, and
并由此引发许多连带问题和风险
there's all sorts of dangers and problems associated with that.
实际上 火星宇的航员
In most real-life scenarios, the Mars astronauts
用不同的太空舱来着陆和起飞
will land and leave in separate crafts.
在长达十八个月的火星考察中
The habitat module, or hab, will be their home during their
生活舱就是宇航员的家
18-month mission on the martian surface.
生活舱备有加压漫游车
They'll take long-range trips in a pressurized rover
他们将用此车进行一次长途旅行
packed along with them on the hab.
一辆小型短程漫游车
A smaller rover, for shorter trips,
已经在着陆点就位
has been pre-positioned at the landing site
旁边就是宇航员的返回舱
along with the astronauts' ride home,
这就是返回地球舱 简称返地舱
the Earth Return Vehicle, or ERV.
它不仅在等待宇航员
The ERV isn't just waiting for the astronauts...
它还在将火星资源转化为火箭燃料和可用空气
It's transforming martian resources into rocket fuel and breathable air.
返地舱有一个泵 能抽进火星的空气
The Earth Return Vehicle runs a pump which sucks in the martian air,
这里二氧化碳含量为95%
which is 95% carbon dioxide gas,
我们可以用这些二氧化碳
and we can react that carbon dioxide gas
和我们从地球带来的少量氢气混合反应
with a small amount of hydrogen that we've brought from Earth
便能产生大量的甲烷 燃料和氧气
to produce a large supply of methane fuel and oxygen.
你的四名宇航员在返地舱附近登陆火星
Your crew of four astronauts land on Mars near the Earth return Vehicle,
他们把生活舱当作实验室和考察基地
they use their habitat as their laboratory, as their exploration base,
考察结束后
but when they're done,
他们就坐返地舱返回地球
they get in the Earth Return Vehicle and they fly back to Earth.
他们将生活舱留在火星上
They leave the hab behind on Mars,
每次探索我们都会为基地增加一个生活舱
so each time we do this we add another hab to the base,
很快
and before you know it
我们就能在火星开始建立人类定居地了
we've got the beginning of the first human settlement on a new world.
我们应该在火星哪里着陆呢
So where should we land on Mars?
火星很令人着迷 那里有许多有趣的地方
Well, Mars is a fascinating planet... There's a lot of interesting areas.
选择赤道附近的地点也许会好一些
It might be better, initially, to choose a region near the equator,
最好是平坦区域 但要靠近地貌奇特的地方
especially a flat area, but also near geologically interesting features.
生活舱降落的技术必须万无一失
One thing that mustn't go wrong is the hab's landing technique,
即大气煞车法
called aerobraking.
大气煞车法是利用火星大气层的摩擦力
Aerobraking is the art of using the friction of the martian atmosphere
降低宇宙飞船的速度
to slow down the spacecraft.
设想这就是进入火星大气层的生活舱
Imagine this ball is the habitat module entering the martian atmosphere.
这根杆子就是火星 非常细小
The pole is Mars, a very skinny Mars.
现在我可以用火箭慢慢降低它的速度
Now, I could use rockets to gently slow this thing down
在预设的地方着陆 也就是胶带的位置
and land at the desired spot, where this duct tape is,
但这就需要许多能量 也就是燃料
but that would require a lot of energy, which requires fuel,
燃料很重且成本高
and that's heavy and expensive.
取而代之 我们可以用火星的大气层来减速
Instead, we could let the martian atmosphere slow the hab down.
看呐 它正在慢慢减速
See that, it's gently slowing down.
而只有在最后 非常接近地表的时候
And only near the very end, when it's getting very close to the surface,
我们才需要用到减速火箭
would we turn on some retrorockets
还有气球降落伞 即气伞
and use a balloon parachute called a ballute
使之在特定位置降落 比如胶带那里
to bring it to the desired location. Like that.
风险就在于 如果进入的角度不对
Now, the danger is that if the angle of entry is wrong
或是速度太快 那么就会导致
or the speed is too fast, then, in fact,
摩擦超过防热罩的承受能力 减速伞和
friction can overwhelm the heat shield, the aeroshell,
舱体会像流星一样在大气层中燃烧起来
and the hab can burn up like a meteor in the martian atmosphere.
只要是微小的计算错误
And even a slight miscalculation
都能导致硬着陆或是在错误地点着陆
can lead to a landing that's too rough or in the wrong place.
着陆过程极其复杂
There's about a thousand things that have to happen.
利用防热罩进入大气层 速度会很快
Come in on a heat shield, going quite fast,
利用大气的摩擦来减速
use the friction of the atmosphere to help slow you down.
要把防热罩抛掉才能着陆
The heat shield, the heat shield needs to be jettisoned.
在穿越大气层时要尽全力制动减速
You need to aerobrake through the atmosphere as much as you can.
通过弹出降落伞来减缓下降速度
You need to pop out a parachute to slow yourself down.
近地面时很可能用到反推火箭
You probably then need retrorockets at the bottom.
落地后要把降落伞割断并丢弃
You need to cut the parachute to get it away from you.
在所有困难的步骤中 这步是难上加难
This is extremely difficult, among the most difficult things there is to do.
但在距离火星表面仅几公里处
Then, a few miles above the surface,
出现了非常困难的状况
something goes very wrong.
生活舱猛地闯入巨大的火星尘暴中
The hab hurtles into a martian dust devil of terrifying proportions.
火星尘暴其实是大气层中的气旋
Dust devils on Mars are vortices in the atmosphere
高速运转的气旋 卷起火星表面的沙尘
so rapidly spinning columns of air that lift dust off of the surface.
然后吹散到大气中
And loft them into the atmosphere.
目前地球上的尘暴高仅一两百米
Now, on Earth, dust devils may only be a few hundred feet high,
但在火星上则高达5至6.5千米
but on Mars, they can be 3 to 4 miles high.
尘暴的规模相当大
So they're simply immense structures.
尘暴吞噬了生活舱
The dust devil engulfs the hab.
将其抛离既定轨道 非常危险
Throwing it dangerously off course.
从德州到哈萨克斯坦的跟踪台
Tracking stations from Texas to Kazakhstan
都密切关注着本次着陆
are following the descent.
但因为火星实在太远
But Mars is so far away,
生活舱信号传输到地球要花费18分钟
it takes 18 minutes for the hab's transmissions to reach Earth.
收到生活舱将要迫降的消息时
When the signal comes through that the hab is headed for a crash-landing,
宇航员们早已迫降着陆了
the astronauts have already crashed.
但是着陆地点在哪 它们是否生还
But where? And are they alive or dead?
起飞和着陆两个过程中
There's only one thing you can do at launch, and there's
我们唯一能做的 只有祈祷
only one thing you can do at landing, and that's pray.
火星探索队:生活舱位置不明
在火星的某处 宇航员们还活着
Somewhere on Mars the astronauts are alive
但联络中断
but communications are out.
他们无法和地球进行联系
They can't talk to Earth.
更糟的是尘暴使他们远离既定路线
Worse, the dust devil has taken them far off course.
人类首次登陆火星 真真正正是一次壮举
When humans first land on Mars, it'll be a truly magnificent event.
这是史无前例的壮举
One of the most historic events ever.
但是 我们的宇航员是紧急迫降的
But, you know, our astronauts crash-landed.
当他们跨出生活舱时
So they're gonna step out
并不知道自己位于何处 发生了什么
not knowing where they are. What's going on.
火星上太阳的亮度仅有地球的一半
The Sun would be about half as bright as it is here.
火星赤道上阳光的强度
The intensity of sunlight at the martian equator
与地球上的挪威或阿拉斯加相当
is about the same as that in Norway on Earth, or Alaska.
火星地表在阴影下
In shadow, everything on Mars
均会呈现黄褐或赤褐色调
would have this kind of yellowish-brown-reddish hue,
只有在阳光直射下才较为显现其原色
and only things in direct sunlight would show their more true color,
这是光线在红色飞尘颗粒中
and that's because the light is being bounced around
反复折射产生的现象
amongst all these reddish dust particles.
这是一幅壮丽的画卷
It'll be a wondrous scene.
但他们无暇欣赏
But they won't have much time to enjoy it.
他们要确定所处的位置
Because they need to figure out where they are,
保证自身安全并计划下步行动
how to get themselves to safety, and what to do.
在火星上没有仪器 怎样找出方位
How do you find out where you are on Mars without instruments?
这些21世纪的宇航员
These 21st-century astronauts
转而求助于一种古老的方法
fall back on an ancient technique.
天文导航
Celestial navigation.
火卫一和火卫二是火星的卫星
The martian moons, Phobos and Deimos,
都运行在赤道轨道上
they're both in equatorial orbits.
它们从正东方升起
The point at which they rise, that would be due east.
从正西方落下
The point at which they set would be due west.
通过计算火卫轨迹顶点与你正上方位的偏差
At their zenith, to the extent they deviated from being directly overhead,
可以得出你所处位置和赤道的距离[纬度]
that would tell you how far you were from the equator.
将火卫升起或降落的时间对照万年历
The time of rise and set, if you compared that to an almanac,
一般电脑上都装有的
which you might have in your computer,
可以得出你所处位置的经度
would tell you your longitude.
结果令人震惊
The results are shocking.
他们身处峡谷的东半部
They have crashed in the eastern half
该峡谷是整个太阳系最大的
of the largest canyon in the Solar System.
1971年被水手9号探测器发现
Discovered in 1971 by the Mariner 9 probe,
并因此命名
and named for it,
水手谷位于火星赤道以南
the Valles Marineris is just south of the martian equator,
深度是美国大峡谷的数倍
several times as deep as the Grand Canyon
长度等同于美国大陆
and as long as the continental United States.
宇航员距离地球返回舱数百公里
The astronauts are hundreds of miles from the Earth Return vehicle.
更糟的是
And there's worse news.
氧气从损坏的生命舱中正在快速流失
The damaged hab is leaking oxygen at a critical rate.
并且无法修复
It can't be repaired.
探索人员数日内可能死亡
The crew could be dead within days.
与火星探索队失去联络时间: 16小时
这是在不久的将来可能发生的一幕
It's a near future scenario that might happen.
第一批人类抵达火星 偏离轨道
The first humans on Mars are hundreds of miles off course.
在水手峡谷里孤立无援
Stranded deep in the gigantic Valles Marineris.
他们无法与地球取得联系
They can't communicate with earth
受损舱体内的空气正在外泄
and their damaged habitat module is leaking air.
几乎每部火星电影都在星球上设计了
Almost every Mars movie imagines a breathable atmosphere
至少一块可呼吸区域
in at least one section of Mars
这样演员就可以把头盔摘掉
so the actors can take off their helmets.
但实际上 火星的大气95%都由二氧化碳构成
But, in fact, Mars' atmosphere is 95% carbon dioxide
与地球三十千米处的大气一样稀薄
and as thin as Earth's atmosphere at 100,000 feet.
我时常惊讶 火星浪漫的景色
I'm often surprised by how caught up we can be by
是那么的令人着迷
this sort of romantic vision of Mars.
这里看着像犹他州或加利福尼亚州
It looks like Utah or California here.
但其实这里是致命的
But the truth is it's a lethal place.
宇航员们只有一次机会
The astronauts have one chance.
他们抓住了
And they take it.
他们组装了一辆漫游车
They assemble the rover,
内有足够使用三周的空气储备
which has a three-week air supply.
一辆密封的漫游车就像旅行房车
A pressurized rover is sort of your RV.
因为你们在车里生活
Uh, you are living inside the rover,
车内加压了 所以可以穿便装
it's pressurized, you're in shirt-sleeves.
开车 生活和工作时
You don't have to be wearing a space suit
你不必身着宇航服
while you're driving it, or living, or working inside.
水手谷:通讯恢复
漫游车运转良好 通讯系统也正常了
The rover is functional and so its communications system.
宇航员通过无线电汇报生还的消息
The astronauts radio home that they are alive.
若漫游车或其中的零部件出了故障
If some component or something goes wrong on it,
备用部件会确保宇航员生还
there is a backup that wouldn't lose the mission.
余度是为了确保安全而考虑的一种设计手段
余度设计是行之有效的方法
So redundancy can be a very good thing,
至少它为困难的解决提供了可能
or at least the ability to design for a failure if you will.
但是对话并不是像阿波罗登月计划里
But the conversations are not like the
不间断地来回问答
constant back and forth of the Apollo Moon missions.
假设这只球代表了信息或对话
Imagine this ball represents a message, a conversation
发生在登月宇航员 也就是我
between an astronaut on the Moon, me,
和德克萨斯州休斯顿控制中心之间
and mission control in Houston, Texas.
现在我距离休斯顿只有几十厘米
Now I'm standing a few inches away from Houston,
但事实上月球在38万公里之外
But, in reality, the Moon is 240,000 miles away.
无线电传输速度等同于光速
Now, radio waves travel at the speed of light,
相当于每秒30万千米
186,000 miles per second.
"你好吗"和"我很好"的问答
So it's only about three seconds
只需耗费3秒钟
between "How are you?" And "I'm fine."
这样对话很简单
Pretty easy to hold a conversation.
但火地的最短距离是地月距离的150倍
But Mars is, at minimum, about 150 times farther away than the moon.
因此我要走出一大段路
So I have to go all the way over to here.
我们仍能交流
We can still communicate,
但出现了更长的延迟
but there's a longer delay.
现实中 火星到地球的距离
In reality, the distance between earth and Mars
在5600万公里到3.8亿公里之间
is between 35 million and 240 million miles.
所以 "你好吗" 和 "我很好"
So the time lag between
之间的时间间隔
"How are you?" and "I'm fine."
会在6到44分钟之间
can be between about 6 and 44 minutes.
这是一段完整的交流需要的时间
That's for a complete exchange.
如果遇到突发状况
So if there's an emergency,
便不能及时解决
it can't be dealt with in real time.
但还有个更大的问题
But there's a bigger problem.
和可见光相同 无线电波只沿直线运动
Like visible light, radio waves travel only in a straight line,
地球和火星都绕轴心旋转
and both Earth and Mars rotate on their axes,
所有有时候两个星球上的人
so there are times when people on the two planets
无法相互交流
can't communicate with each other.
我们可以用两颗定位卫星解决这个问题
We can solve this with two properly positioned satellites.
假设一颗卫星围绕火星运转
If there's a satellite orbiting Mars,
信息能从火星传到休斯顿的指挥中心
a message can be sent from mars to mission control in Houston.
信息从火星轨道卫星发出
It gets sent to that satellite orbiting Mars,
传到地球轨道卫星
then to the Earth orbiting satellite,
最后传到指挥中心 再往复传递
then to mission control, and back again.
现在 问题发出与回答
Now, there's still a time delay
仍有段多达44分钟的时间延迟
of up to 44 minutes between question and answer,
但至少火星宇航员和
but at least the Mars astronaut and
指挥中心能制定出一个生存计划
mission control can formulate a survival plan.
解决了通讯延迟的问题
Working through the communication lag,
计划成型了
the plan takes shape.
为燃料电池驱动的漫游车装上食物和仪器
Load the fuel-cell powered rover with food and equipment,
并向东行驶到
and drive it east to where the
水手谷注入的一个外流峡谷
Valles Marineris empties into an outflow valley,
这个峡谷可能是十亿年前形成的
probably carved out billion of years ago,
那时火星的大气层更厚
when Mars had a thicker atmosphere
液态水仍在其表面流淌
and liquid water still flowed on its surface.
从这里出发
From this exit point,
驶向返地舱的原始着陆地点
it's less than a day's drive to the Earth return Vehicle
时间不足一天
at the original landing site.
你可以想象这段横穿火星大陆的绝望之旅
So you can imagine having a desperate trip across the Martian landscape
为的是重新回到返地舱上
to get back to the Return Vehicle
可能会做点科学研究
and perhaps do a little bit of scientific research
但最重要的是保全自己并返回地球
but most importantly, save yourself and get back to Earth.
所有事情都取决于一些残酷的客观条件
Everything depends on some very cold equations.
每名宇航员每天需要11升水
Each astronaut has a daily need for 3 gallons of water,
两千卡路里的食物 和900克的氧气
2,000 calories of food, and 2 pounds of oxygen.
生存性技术能发挥作用
Survival technology can help.
它们用漫游车车载的装置
They can extract water from Mars itself
从火星提取水
using equipment on-board the rover.
火星探测器显示
The Mars Odyssey spacecraft has shown
火星赤道区的尘土中 水的质量约占6%
that average Martian dirt in the equatorial regions is 6% water by weight.
如果想从中提取出水
So if you want to get water out of that
你只需采集一些尘土
you can just take some of it
将其放入一口类似高压锅的带盖容器中
and throw it into a pot like a pressure cooker with a led
加热到150度 水就提取出来了
and heat it to, you know, 150 centigrade and you get out the water.
如果放入11升的尘土
And if you put in about 2 gallons of dirt,
就会得到470毫升的水
you'll get about a pint of water.
但是在火星上
But other human needs
满足人类的其他需要却没这么简单
are not so easily supplied on Mars.
一次为期两周的旅行
Certainly on a two-week journey,
若要成功横穿火星的荒凉之境
if you had to make it across a desolate Martian landscape,
你可以减少食物摄入
you could cut down on food.
留用饥饿时充饥
You could have starvation rations.
甚至可以减少饮水量
You can even cut down on water.
但唯一时时刻刻不可或缺的是空气
But the one thing that you absolutely need, minute by minute, is air.
你无法控制身体所需空气量
You have no flexibility in the amount of air that you need to
以供特殊时期使用
make it for a specific amount of time.
除了要到达返地舱的需要
Despite the need to get to the ERV,
还有足够的空气供数次舱外短时操作
there is enough air for several brief EVAs, or extra vehicular activities.
把人们送上火星的部分理由是
Part of the reason for sending people to Mars
做些令人信服的科学研究
would be to do some compelling science,
我们可以设想他们采集样分析样品
so we would imagine them taking samples, analyzing them,
试图了解岩石形成时的环境
trying to understand the environment when those rocks formed.
诸如此类的事
Things like that.
宇航员使用各种各样的工具
Astronauts could use a whole variety of tools,
锤子 放大镜 不同种类的分普仪
hammers, hand lenses, spectrometers of various sorts,
以及化学分析仪器
chemical analysis machines.
漫游车上可能会有移动实验室
There'd be probably some mobile laboratory on the rover
宇航员们用采集的材料
that would use the materials that they gathered
观察其物质构成 诸如此类
to look at the composition, and so on.
关于水手峡谷的形成
There's a number of theories as to how the, uh,
有许多理论
Valles Marineris was created.
对结构如何形成仍然一知半解
It's still not fully clear how the structure came to be, but,
在大部分的可能性中 涉及到诸多过程
in most likelihood, quite a few processes were involved.
我认为 做野外地质学研究对真正了解
I think that being on the ground and doing field geology is
像水手峡谷一样复杂地形的形成过程
essential to really understanding the processes that had
是必不可少的
sculpt a complex landform like the Valles Marineris.
这个过程很复杂
It's not a simple story.
这不只是地上的一个裂缝
It wasn't just a crack in the earth,
也不只是流体流动形成的
it wasn't just fluid flowed in and formed that.
不同的过程
There were different processes,
发生在不同时间
acting at different times,
分层堆积在彼此之上 形成一本复杂的书
layering on top of each other, forming a complex book.
为了阅读这本书
And in order to read that book,
你需要到那里将书页翻开[实地考察]
you really need to be there to turn the pages.
水手谷的不同部分变化多样
Valles Marineris has a whole variety of different segments.
中间部分 有一 二 三
There's places in the middle that there's one, two, three, or
甚至四处坎坷不平的平行峡谷
even four parallel canyons where you go down and up
经过那里需要不停地上去下来
and down and up and down and up.
最东部的尽头
And then, at the very eastern end,
看起来像是河流从混沌区域涌出
it looks like water came flushing out through what would be a chaos zone,
灾难性的洪水也许曾在此发生
catastrophic floods of water that might have come out.
水中曾有生命的存在吗
Was there life in that water?
他们挖出的岩石样本能充分证明
Could some of the rock samples they dig up have enough evidence
石化细菌的存在吗
of fossilized bacteria?
火星曾是一个温暖潮湿的行星
Mars was once a warm and wet planet,
这是因为
and we know that for a fact
水侵蚀的特征遍布火星表面
because there are water erosion features all over the surface of Mars.
为了寻找有生命的化石
To look for fossils of life,
你需要找一些有水流过或是聚积的地方
you want to look for places where water has flown or accumulated,
水手峡谷或许是其中一个地方
and the Valles Marineris might be one of those places.
他们在地表之下能找到
Is it even possible that they will find evidence of
液态水的迹象吗
liquid water under the surface?
水中 会有生物体吗
And in that water... Living organisms?
稳定的液态水环境中 都有生命形成吗
Will life form anywhere that liquid water is stable?
或者 会有亿万分之一的机会形成生命体吗
Or is there a one-in-a-trillion chance occurrence that leads to life?
火星上曾有另一个起源吗
Was there a second genesis on Mars?
我认为现在火星上完全可能有细菌活动
I think it's certainly possible that there's bacterial activity on Mars now,
但绝对不是确定的
but that's by no means certain.
这是个非常有趣的现代科学问题
It's... it's a very interesting current scientific question.
我觉得这是太阳系科学中最让人着迷的
I think it's one of the sort of most intriguing questions
一个问题
in solar system science.
水手峡谷 三级红色警报
突然 为了生存
Suddenly, the search for life pauses
生命的探索中止了
as the fight for survival resumes.
指挥中心发出信号
Mission control signals that
一个高度危险的太阳耀斑喷向火星
a high risk solar flare is headed for Mars.
一个太阳耀斑是太阳小型区域
A solar flare is a tremendous outburst
所发生的一次猛烈活动
from a relatively small region of the Sun.
一股巨大的能量迸发出来
A huge amount of energy goes pouring out explosively,
随之而来的就是一股带电粒流
and a bunch of energetic charged particles
穿越太阳系
go zooming through the solar system.
它们可以与细胞反应 造成伤害
They can interact with cells and harm them.
还会产生像X射线一样的超强电磁辐射
Also, high-energy electromagnetic radiation like x-rays gets produced,
同样对我们有害
and those can harm us as well.
所以有两个能量波 接连而来
So it's "Wham!" and then "Wham!" again sometime later.
地磁场可以抵消太阳耀斑大部分影响
Earth's magnetic field shields us from the worst effects of solar flares.
但是火星四十亿年前就没有了磁场
But Mars lost its magnetic field 4 billion years ago.
在地球上的人们观测到太阳耀斑活动后
After a solar flare is seen by people on Earth,
我们想要警告火星上的宇航员
we want to warn the astronauts on Mars.
但是我们无法预警他们将有电磁辐射
Now we can't warn them about the electromagnetic flash because
因为预警信号的传输速度和电磁辐射相同
our warning signal would travel at the same speed as that flash from the Sun,
但是我们可以警告他们带电粒子风暴来袭
but we can warn them about the onslaught of charged particles.
高能带电粒子风暴的速度 差不多是
The high-energy charged particles can travel, perhaps,
光速的一半
at half the speed of light.
生活舱设有防辐射舱
The hab has a radiation-proof chamber,
但是现在距离太远
but it's now too far away.
尽管太空服可以使宇航员免遭太阳耀斑辐射
While the astronauts' space suits shielded them from the solar flare's x-rays,
但他们现在只有几分钟
they have only minutes to seek shelter
在第二波高能粒子到达火星前寻找庇护所
before the flare's high-energy second wave slams into Mars.
如果在未来 人类登陆火星紧急迫降
If a future human mission to Mars crash-lands,
宇航员面对的不只是
the astronauts will have to contend
严酷的火星地貌环境
with even more than the harsh martian landscape.
太阳耀斑的质子风暴在火星的威力
A solar flare of charged protons would be far more dangerous here
水手峡谷: 耀斑粒子流来袭倒计时: 7分钟
比地球强的多
than on Earth.
因为火星并不具备像地球一样的地磁场
Well, Mars doesn't have a magnetic field like the Earth does
那么所有那些高能粒子和带电粒子流
so all of these high energetic particles and these charged particles
将会直接轰击火星表面
would be hitting the surface directly
并且伤害到那些在火星地面的宇航员
and hitting any astronauts that we had on the surface.
他们将完全暴露在这些危险的太阳射线和
They would not be protected from all of these dangerous rays and
带电粒子流中
these dangerous particles,
而在地球 我们有地磁场的良好保护
whereas on Earth, we're comfortably protected by our magnetic field.
如果地表宇航员接触高能粒子流
There are a number of bad effects that would come about
将会有许多严重的后果发生
from the energetic particles hitting an astronaut on the surface.
比如 增加患癌症的几率 或者其他疾病
Increased rates of cancer, for example, or other diseases, uh,
辐射病 辐射中毒
radiation sickness, and radiation poisoning.
事实上 在空间站的宇航员
In fact, astronauts aboard the space station
偶尔也会进入到一个特别的舱室
have occasionally been told to hide in special chambers
使其免遭来自太阳的带电粒子流
to protect them against the charged particles
和电磁辐射的伤害
and radiation coming from the solar flare.
对于那些在火星水手峡谷中的宇航员来说
For the astronauts in the middle of the Valles marineris,
唯一的保护装置就是他们的加压漫游车
the only shelter is their pressurized rover.
保护宇航员的并不是漫游车原辐射保护层
The rover's primary radiation shielding isn't lead.
而是墙上摆得食物包
It's the food packets lining the walls,
以及宇航员的排泄物提供了保护
along with the astronauts' own waste material.
排泄物种含有烃类 而烃类中则有氢
Feces contain hydrocarbons, and hydrocarbons contain hydrogen,
而氢是一种很好的辐射吸收剂
and hydrogen is a very good absorber of radiation.
还没有被食用的食物中的氢元素
Hydrogen that you have in the form of food before it's consumed
将会为你抵挡一部分辐射带来的危害
will help shield you from some portion of this radiation,
当然 当你把食物食用后
and certainly once you've consumed your food
应该把排泄物放进
you want to put your feces
那些在漫游车上的墙中的小格子里
in these little tilble zip-blocks and back on the wall of the vehicle
来保护你们免遭辐射
to shield you from radiation.
如果你想在宇宙中活命
If you're going to survive in space,
任何东西都得派上用场啊
almost nothing can go to waste.
包括排泄物
Not even waste.
紧急危机过去了
With the immediate crisis over,
宇航员们继续前往返地舱地点
the journey to the Earth Return Vehicle continues.
水手号峡谷 任务计划改变
然而 又有意想不到的事发生了
Then, something unexpected happens.
宇航员们投票表决后改变了计划
The astronauts take a vote and change the plan.
指令长:休斯顿指挥中心
我们做出了一个决定我们一致决定不立即返回地球
他们不愿搭返地舱提前500天回到地球
Rather than using the ERV to fly home 500 days ahead of schedule,
他们要在火星上坚持完成任务
they will stay and complete de mission.
火星行动的后援团队对
The team backup on the space is gonna have much less knowledge
探索队情况和他们面临的选择知之甚少
of the circumstances of the crew and the real options opened to them
只有他们自己最清楚
than the crew themselves have.
所以我觉得应从前线指挥火星探索队
So I think that a Mars mission is gonna have to be commanded from the front,
而这样的话 与其设立控制中心
and that, rather than having a mission control,
我们需要一个任务支持中心
we need to have a mission support.
宇航员们的新计划是到达返地舱所在地
The astronauts' new plan is to make it to the Earth return Vehicle
并用其代替生命舱 作为他们的行动基地
and use it, in place of the hab, as their base of operations.
返地舱要比生活舱小许多
It's much smaller than the hab,
但它有电力供给 并能产生额外氧气
but it has a power supply and it has the ability to make extra oxygen.
所以事实上 探索队可以使用返地舱
So the crew could, in fact, go to the Earth Return Vehicle
生活并进行工作
and live in it and work out of it.
水手峡谷外流渠道
宇航员对他们的生存抱有极大信心
The astronauts' confidence on their survival shoots up.
因为他们到达了水手谷东部的外流渠道
As they reach the outflow channel at the eastern edge of Valles Marineris.
食物水源和空气都还充足
There's enough food, water, and air
到返地舱绰绰有余
to make an easy drive to the ERV.
这时 一名宇航员看到了不寻常的事物
Then, an astronaut sees something unusual.
有一块暴露在外的岩石层
An exposed layer of rock that looks like it might contain
可能包含叠层石
something called stromatolites.
在地球上 有细菌存在
On Earth, we had bacteria,
而且不只是单细胞细菌
and not just individual bacteria
还有多细胞菌群落 它们造出了岩石
but bacteria that formed colonies, which created rocks
也就是叠层石
known as stromatolites.
这些东西 可以说是细菌界的珊瑚礁
These are, you might call, the bacterial equivalent of coral reefs,
由微小的生物体造出的大物体
where tiny organisms build up something big.
如果火星上应该存在这种东西
This would be a logical thing to look for on Mars.
在地球上有叠层石 这也是我们期望
Stromatolites on Earth provide the kind of evidence
在火星上找到的某种证据
that we would expect to see on Mars,
不是说一定要有 但这是基本的理论
not on that exact form, but it's the basic idea.
叠层石相当于无数细菌尸体
Stromatolites were sort of massive LOG
转为硅质形态堆积
and then silicon-like material but built up
形成宏观结构 随即这样保存了下来
and formed macroscopic structures which were then preserved.
如果说类似过程曾在火星发生
If something like that was going on on Mars,
我们就能很肯定的说
that would provide an easy way of determining that
那里曾经有生命存在
life did indeed exist there.
很多科幻电影题材都是源于
Many science-fiction films are based
我们在火星上发现了存在先进文明的证据
on the idea that we'll find evidence of advanced civilizations on Mars.
火星上并没有城市或是规模化建筑的迹象
Mars has no cities or grand structures.
但宇航员或许能找到火星存在生命的证据
But astronauts may yet find evidence of life on Mars...
哪怕是只能找到细菌化石
Even if it's only fossils of bacteria.
宇航员们采集到了岩石样本
With the rock samples loaded in,
漫游车准备出发 但却停止不动
the rover tries to head off... But goes nowhere.
一个轮子陷住了
One wheel is stuck.
宇航员束手无策
The astronauts cannot free it.
沙子是火星上的死亡陷阱
Sand is sort of the death trap of Mars,
我可以预见到
and I wouldn't be surprised if, you know,
在未来的登陆中 会有一些宇航员因为
in future expeditions, we end up losing some crews that are on
漫游车陷入沙障中而命丧火星
these long pressurized rover traverses to sand traps.
他们记算了一下从这里到返地舱的距离
They calculate the remaining distance to the ERV.
他们能徒步平安返回吗
Could they walk to safety?
满载氧气的太空服只能支持十二小时
A space suit's full tank of air will only last 12 hours.
而这段距离需要持续徒步三十个小时
It would take 30 hours of continuous walking.
当你在地球上考察各种地形时
On the Earth, you can get stuck
会在沙漠地带抛锚
when you are doing all-terraining in sandy areas.
但是 在地球上
But, of course, on the Earth,
你大以可停下 吸口新鲜空气
you can just step outside the vehicle and breathe.
在火星上却不行
On Mars, you won't have that option.
所以如果你的车被卡住了
So if your vehicle is stuck,
并且无法脱困
and there's no way to get it out of its predicament,
你只能眼睁睁地等死
you're gonna watch yourself die.
水手峡谷外流渠道
在我们设想的人类首次登火可能出现的问题中
In our scenario of what might go wrong for the first human mission to Mars,
宇航员漫游车陷入火星沙地
the astronauts' rover is trapped in the Martian sand.
返地舱却在160公里远之外
The Earth Return Vehicle is 100 miles away.
宇航员必死无疑吗
Are the astronauts facing certain death,
还是他们能利用工业化前的技术再次脱险呢
or can they save themselves once again with pre-industrial technology?
假设探险队陷入困境
So let's say the crew was stranded
至少需要一人
and they need to get at least one person,
长途跋涉去找到另一辆车
a considerable distance to secure another vehicle
再回来解救其余的人
and come back and rescue the rest.
气球式降落伞能否堪此重任
Could they do this with ballutes?
只是有可能
It's just possible.
地球上的工程师进行了一些测试
Engineers on Earth run tests to see
看一个气球是否能运载至少一名宇航员
if a balloon could carry at least one astronaut
穿过沙漠到达返地舱
over the desert to the ERV.
通过伸展一张包裹着气体二氧化碳的
You could do this by stretching a synthetic membrane of some sort
人造膜来做到这一点
around a pocket of the surrounding air, just carbon dioxide.
你得加热其中的气体来
And then you'd have to heat the air inside
使它产生浮力
in order to give it some sort of buoyancy.
现在可以使用太阳能加热
Now, one way of doing that is having solar heating
令薄膜有效地吸收太阳能
effectively have the membrane absorb solar energy,
加热其中的二氧化碳
heat the carbon dioxide inside
然后薄膜膨胀融合 气球升起
and then it expands, becomes blend and lifts the balloon up.
在火星制造的气球
Any balloon that you would construct to fabricate on Mars
是非常巨大的
would have to be very large
因为这样才能弥补那里的极低大气密度
to compensate for the very low density atmosphere.
火星大气层非常稀薄
The Martian atmosphere is very thin.
比地球海平面大气压的1%还低
It's less than 1% of Earth's atmospheric pressure at sea level.
那意味着为了举起重物
That means that to get substantial lift,
你需要一个庞大的气球
you need an enormous balloon.
对一个身着太空服的宇航员来说
A balloon that is 10 meters in radius is probably enough for
也许一个半径十米的气球足矣
one astronaut in a space suit.
为什么火星小队会有个如此巨大的气球
Why would a crew on Mars have a balloon that big?
他们也许没有
They probably wouldn't,
但他们也许会有大量
but they might have a large number of balloons used
小型用于科研的气球
for scientific purposes that were smaller than that.
这个冒险计划被付诸行动
The risky plan is put into action.
一名宇航员用临时伞带 升上火星的天空
In a makeshift harness, one astronaut rises into the Martian sky.
在1.6千米高空
A mile up,
风吹着她以每小时96公里的速度
winds blow her towards the ERV
前往返地舱
at 60 miles an hour.
火星表面的盛行风从西吹向东
On Mars, the prevailing winds near the surface blow from West to east,
我们正想如此 所以那对我们有利
and we want to go from west to east. So that's good for us.
这个方案存在个大问题
One of the big problems with this scenario
就是你达到目的地的精确度
is the precision at which you could hope to, uh, reach your destination.
如果你能降落在徒步到达的距离之内
But if you could then come down within hiking distance of your destination...
这需要一些运气 但也有可能
It'd take some luck, but it's possible.
火星重力只有地球的百分之三十八
Mars has only 38% of Earth's gravity.
科幻电影常常忽略这个事实
Science-fiction movies usually forget that fact,
让宇航员在正常的好莱坞重力下行动
and have astronauts operate in normal Hollywood gravity.
事实是 就算穿上沉重的
The truth is, even with the heavy space suits
舱外活动太空服
worn during extra vehicular activity,
在火星上步行也比在地球上容易得多
hiking on Mars will be easier than on Earth.
假如你体重68公斤
Let's say you're a 150-pound person
穿上90公斤的太空服
and you put on a 200 pound suit...
就是160公斤
That's 350 pounds.
但是如果你只有那重量的38%
But then, if you only weigh 38% of that,
那么你加上制服的重量就只是55公斤
okay, then your weight is maybe 120 pounds with the suit.
所以你穿着制服在火星上步行
So you actually have less of a burden walking with that suit on Mars
要比在地球上轻装徒步更轻松
than you have walking in your stockings on Earth.
返地舱位置 已到达
宇航员成功着陆
The astronaut lands successfully
成功到达返地舱和双人漫游车
and manages to hike to the ERV and the two person rover.
一切设备正常工作
Everything is in working order.
其中一名宇航员驾驶沙漠漫游车
So one of the astronauts gets into a dune buggy rover,
回到被困的加压漫游车旁
comes back to the pressurized rover,
带上其中一名宇航员 将他带向返地舱
takes one of the astronauts, brings that astronaut to the Earth Return Vehicle
然后来回几趟
then goes back and forth a couple of more times
将所有的宇航员都安全带回
to get all the astronauts over to safety.
计划就是如此
That's the plan.
但是新的危险出现了
But then a new danger arises,
一场红尘暴
a storm of red dust.
空中太阳越来越暗淡 沙尘越来越厚
The Sun would get dimmer in the sky, and it would continue to build and build,
向一望无际的天边望去
and you'd see, from horizon to horizon,
浓厚的沙尘在大气中形成巨大的漩涡
this very thick dusty swirly mass in the atmosphere.
但是什么引发了火星的沙尘暴
But what causes dust storms on Mars?
加州阿纳海姆的丽莎·阿布多发达
That's what Lisa Abdelfatah of Anaheim,
在电邮中写道
California, emailed
询问宇宙
是什么引起了火星的沙尘暴
丽莎 你也许会大吃一惊
Lisa, you might be surprised to learn that
因为是太阳的能量引发了火星上的尘暴
dust storms on Mars are actually caused by energy from the Sun.
太阳炙烤火星表面的沙尘和大气层
The Sun heats the dust in the surface of Mars and also that atmosphere,
导致它膨胀并产生对流现象
causing it to expand and causing convection currents to occur,
在不同的空气之间存在的不同压力
and there are difference of pressure between one pocket of air and another,
于是产生了风
that leads to winds.
接着沙尘越来越厚 越来越热
Then more dust gets kicked up and more heating
压力差越来越大
and more of these pressure differences,
最终导致猛烈的沙尘暴
so you get these violent dust storms.
火星的沙尘对宇航员来说非常危险
The dust on Mars could be very hazardous to astronauts
其中有很多原因
for a number of reasons.
因为火星没有水
Because there's no water on Mars,
每颗沙粒不像你在地球海滩上看到的
the individual grains are not smooth and rounded like...
那么光滑圆润
Like you would see on a beach here on Earth.
它们真的很尖锐且有锯齿
They're actually very sharp and jagged.
宇航员步行或者活动的时
As that dust gets kicked up as the astronaut's walking or moving,
激起的沙尘存留在太空服上
uh, it gets caught on the space suit.
一段时间之后 由于摩擦
And, over time, due to friction...
比如宇航员在摆动胳膊或者迈腿的时候
Let's say the astronaut's moving arms or his legs...
沙尘就开始侵蚀太空服的纤维
Uh, it begins to eat away at the fabric of the space suit.
这样太空服就很容易撕破或开裂
So you could easily get a tear or a rip in the space suit,
而那将会是灾难性的
and that would be catastrophic.
尽管危机重重 宇航员还是驾着小型漫游车
Despite the dangers, the astronaut takes the small rover,
载着额外的氧气补给 冲入沙尘暴
loaded with extra oxygen, out into the storm.
她一个一个地把队友接回返地舱
And one by one, she brings her crew mates back to the Earth Return Vehicle.
但是就在即将到达安全地点时
But just a few feet from safety...
粗糙的沙尘就撕破了指挥官的太空服
The abrasive dust tears a section of the commander's suit,
将他暴露在几近真空的火星大气层下
exposing him to the near-vacuum of the martian atmosphere.
如果你的太空服有一个漏洞
If... If your space suit springs a leak,
或者它突然降压 完全打开了
or if it's a violent decompression, where your suit is ripped open,
你只能保持几秒清醒
you might not have more than a few seconds to remain conscious
来面对将会发生的事
and see what's going to happen to you.
你情况不妙
You would be in a very bad way.
好似在地球上深度潜水后上浮
You would be not dissimilar to coming up from a very deep dive on the Earth.
这将是一次非常痛苦的经历
It would be a very painful experience.
如果你有减压问题
If you have a decompression problem
这将是很严重且致命的
it can get very serious and lethal.
你将面临可怕而迅速的死亡
You would die a horrible death and very quickly as well.
除非他的同伴能马上采取措施
Unless his crew mates can do something immediately,
否则他将会成为火星上的第一具人类尸体
the commander will be the first human corpse on Mars.
在我们对不远未来的设想中
In our scenario of the near future,
首批登陆火星的探索者
the first explorers on Mars
同时经受住了近乎致命的撞击
have survived a near fatal crash
与在这充满敌意的星球上的危险旅程
and a dangerous trek across a hostile planet.
但如今 一场磨蚀性砂尘形成的风暴
But now, a storm of abrasive dust
在任务指挥官的太空服上撕开了一个洞
has torn a hole in mission commander's spacesuit.
这是宇航员最为害怕的情况
It's the one thing the astronauts fear above everything else.
失去意识前 你只有10到12秒的时间
You've got 10 or 12 seconds before you lose consciousness.
这种情况下最好立即呼气 排空肺部
You better exhale, right away. Empty your lungs,
不然的话它们便会迅速扩张乃至爆裂
because otherwise they'll quickly expand and rupture.
太空服破损十二秒后 指挥官已不省人事
Twelve seconds after his suit tore, the commander is unconscious.
他的皮肤开始发青
His skin is turning blue.
他的组员只有不到九十秒的时间
His crewmates have less than 90 seconds
将他送进返地舱的气闸室
to get him through the ERV's airlock
进行紧急输氧 否则他的血液循环将停止
and administer emergency oxygen before his blood circulation ceases
他的器官将永久地停止工作
and his organs shut down forever.
在失去意识之后
After you've lost consciousness,
最好有人能在接下来的一分半钟内
you hope that someone will hook you up to pressurized oxygen
为你提供压缩氧气
within the next minute and a half.
如果得不到的话 你必死无疑
If you don't get hooked up, you'll die for sure.
若能得到救助 并能再次呼吸氧气
If you do get hooked up, and you start breathing oxygen again,
等你挺过来 一般来说
it turns out that, when you come to,
不会造成太多的永久性伤害
there's usually not much permanent damage.
指挥官在千钧一发之际得以幸存
The commander survives with seconds to spare.
尽管他受伤了 他还是能够痊愈
Despite his injuries, he will make a full recovery.
火星基地一号 任务进行中
很快 队员们恢复了精力
Soon, the crew is back to full strength,
并开始进行各种实验活动
working and performing experiments.
火星探索已正式展开
The exploration of Mars has begun in earnest.
对我来说火星将会挑战一切
Mars to me would challenge
人类历史上有过的探索经验
all the expedition experiences that we've had throughout our history.
过往积累的宝贵经验均会尽数应用
It will take all the best lessons learned from all past expeditions.
比如极地经验 丛林经验
The polar ones, the ones through the jungles,
以及北美大陆经验
the ones through North America.
火星是个极具挑战性的地方 它极度无情
Mars is a super-challenging place; it's very unforgiving.
在地球上 即便遇上麻烦
Here on Earth, if things go wrong,
我们仍有空气可呼吸 仍有水源可饮用
we can rely on there being air to breathe and water to drink.
但在火星上 如果出了问题
On Mars, if something goes wrong,
那么情况马上会变得更加糟糕
then the situation is automatically much more serious.
但是宇航员已证明他们能适应火星上的环境
But the astronauts have proven that they can adapt to the martian environment.
和极地探索者一样 他们抵御着刺骨低温
Like polar explorers, they protect themselves from the frigid temperatures.
像沙漠探索者一样
Like desert explorers,
他们学会与无处不在的砂尘共同生活
they learn to live with the ever-present dust.
在我们火星协会运作的沙漠研究站里
In our own desert station that the Mars Society runs
我们带去一台高端显微镜
we brought a really superb microscope,
但是运抵之后数周之内 它就被砂尘弄坏了
but it was disabled by dust within a few weeks of it's arrival.
而另一方面 一些工艺更为粗糙的显微镜
On the other hand, some much cruder kind of microscopes,
类似于一般本科学生用的一类
similar to the kind that college students use routinely,
经证实相当强韧
have proved very robust.
在前线环境中 你想要的不会是匹赛马
In a frontier environment, you don't want to bring a racehorse.
你想要的会是匹骡子
You want to bring a mule.
然而火星上也不见得处处都比地球艰难
Not everything on Mars is more difficult than on Earth.
例如地表风就十分柔和 根本无法对
The surface winds, for instance, are mild, too weak to threaten
宇航员或是他们的器械造成威胁
the astronauts or their instruments.
火星大气层的厚度只有地球大气的百分之一
The martian atmosphere is only 1% as thick as Earth's atmosphere,
所以说如果你站在地上
and so if you're on the ground
对面96公里每小时的风刮过来时
and a 60 mile an hour wind kicked up,
你只会有10公里每小时的风轻拂的感觉
you would only feel the force of a 6 mile an hour wind.
我们这有个风速计 或是叫测风速计
We have here an anemometer, or wind-gage
用来测量当前风速
which helps us measure the wind speed.
它的设计实际上很简单
It's a very simple design really.
上面的这些风杯在风刮过的时候
You've got these cups on top that capture the wind
捕捉风力从而使得风杯旋转
as it blows by and causes the cups to spin.
你只用记下风杯的旋转次数
You simply count the number of rotations of the cups,
它就能显示出当前风速
and it gives you the wind speed.
它的设计非常简单
It's a very simple design,
与19世纪刚发明的时候基本一样
very much the same as the one that was invented back in the 1800s,
只是没有这个数字读数器
except, of course, with this digital readout.
看看我们能不能测得到这的风速吧
Well, let's see if we can get some wind here.
有了 这里有阵风
Oh, there we got some! Oh, here comes a gust.
因为火星大气层较地球大气层要稀疏得多
Because the atmosphere is so much less dense,
因此作用在风力计上的空气分子就少得多
and you have far fewer molecules of air sort of blowing on the anemometer,
地球上3公里每小时的风给人的感觉
You would need a 20 mile an hour wind on Mars to feel
在火星上要32公里每小时的风才能做到
what a 2 mile an hour wind would feel like on Earth.
你可以看到这个速度下的风
So you can see the wind that's blowing at that speed is sort of
只能稍稍弄乱你的头发
lightly mussing your hair.
而你要是在火星上
If you were to have this on Mars,
要达到同样的效果的话
a similar wind speed that would give you the same sort of effect
风速大约要有112公里每小时
would be about a 70 mile an hour wind.
也就是飓风风速
So that's hurricane speed.
宇航员要做的不仅仅是适应火星的环境
The astronauts do more than adapt to Mars.
他们从火星表面提取水源
They extract water from the surface,
并用火星土壤种植食物
and use martian soil to grow food.
就种植食物来说
Now, in terms of growing food,
最容易种植的是像生菜一样的带叶植物
the things that can be grown most easily are leafy things like lettuce.
在未来的某一时段人们会开始种植土豆
At a certain point you're gonna want to grow potatoes, which can
这能使农场里平方米淀粉产量得到极大增长
create a great deal of starch per square meter of farmland.
一年前在火星上 只有四人绝境求生
A year ago on Mars, four humans struggled to survive.
如今 他们开始在那里繁荣生息
Now, they are beginning to make a planet bloom.
但这只是个开始
But it's only a beginning.
近一个世纪来 电影一直有构想和希望
For over a century, movies have perpetuated the idea, and the hope,
即火星上有智慧生物存在
that there is intelligent life on Mars.
目前这里还没有
There isn't, yet.
但在本世纪末的某个时候
But sometime late in this century,
两位来自地球的人类的结合
two people from Earth
有可能诞生出首位火星人
might give birth to the first martian
它可能是很多新事物的起源
who may be the first of many more.
我们将是火星人
We will be the martians.
但这是未来的远景
But that's the future.
对于第一个任务来说 时间快不够了
For this first mission, time is running short.
火星基地一号 返程开始
地球与火星处于返程的同一直线上
Earth and Mars are at the right alignment for the journey home.
宇航员们希望能一头扎进
The astronauts look forward to splashing down on the warm
太平洋温暖的水域里
waters of the Pacific ocean.
正当他们向着浩瀚宇宙中
As they head back to that bright blue ball
那颗明亮的蓝色星球进发时
in the star-sprinkled blackness,
另一道光却朝着相反的方向闪过
another streak of light heads the other way.
火星探索队2 第一天
这是装载有另一台返地舱的
It's the second manned mission heading for a rendezvous
向着集结点前进的第二次载人探索任务
with another pre-positioned ERV.
载人火星探索有相当多的危险
There's plenty of risks associated with a human Mars mission.
但如果你着眼人类历史
But if you look at human history,
有一点是很明确的
you know, one thing is clear,
即伟业必有险阻
nothing great has ever been accomplished without risk,
创举必须勇气
and nothing great has ever been accomplished without courage.
如果我们能够在这一代将人送上火星
If we sent humans to Mars in our time,
如果我们能够在火星上定居下来
if we establish that little planet rock settlement on mars in our time
这是我们能做到的
which is what within our capability,
那么五百年后在火星以至于更多星球
then 500 years from now there would be new branches of
都会诞生出人类文明的新枝节
human civilization on Mars and on many worlds beyond.
这将会是未来的曙光
It's the birth of the future.